good.
All right, well, welcome,
everybody, to our session
on Inventing Eliza, which serves
as a kind of yellow book launch for us.
And it's it's a pleasure to be here.
We give our great thanks to the organizers
of this conference.
You guys have been tireless
while exhausted.
So. And I'm just so, so grateful to you
for all of your work.
Let me share screen
and we'll get ourselves started.
So our presentation is called.
I think you're in the last slide.
Oh, yeah.
Let me get to the first slide.
Okay, here we go.
But but no, but I did.
I have another slide that said
even the title of our talk is now I'm
forgetting.
Anyway, our talk is called something
About Inventing Eliza.
And here you see
the names of all of our team members.
We are not all here.
But I'm going to have everybody
introduce themselves in just one second.
First, I'll show you a little screenshot
of what we all look like.
Some of us, when we're holding up
our copies of our book,
and some of us when we're not.
Oh, wait, someone did.
Someone had a book to Sarah.
Picture. Great. Yeah. Okay.
All right. Well.
But so as a way of getting started,
let's go around
and everyone can can introduce themselves.
Let's let's go if we can.
And I don't know,
alphabetic order. David.
Yeah.
So I'm a professor of digital humanities
here in the UK
at the University of Sussex.
And with my esteemed colleagues
we have written Inventing Eliza,
a project that we've been working on for,
well, four years.
Solid on the book, but much, much longer
than that, and some even longer than lung.
Jeff, I'm looking at you and
I work on various forms
of computational media
critical code studies, software studies,
and the philosophy of technology.
Excellent.
And my, my Alphabet's breaking down
because we have so many.
We have. Jeff.
You're next. No.
Oh! Oh, I was going to go last. What?
I was going to go last. Oh, okay.
All right. Whatever.
Jeff Schrager what David was obliquely
referring to is I
when I was 13, in middle school,
which was a long time ago,
we didn't learn to program in the womb
at that time.
I wrote a really bad
knockoff of Eliza in Basic,
which became famous
just because of the timing of the.
It was like viral,
as we would call it now.
And so but I didn't think of Eliza
for a long time after that.
And we'll get back to the why.
I came back to it
because David basically said to me,
oh, we're going to review your Eliza
in one of our code studies group.
And I said, well, that's ridiculous.
Why don't you review the original?
And he said, we don't have the original
and the rest is history.
Nice.
I believe that puts you all right.
I'm was basically
a developer, all kinds of systems.
I became intrigued in this when Jeff,
a man that I truly disliked, called me up
and said
I developed a version of slipped,
which I made public, and he said,
are you interested?
And I said, yes.
So slip is the language
that Eliza the code?
It's an application programing which Eliza
uses in its code
to give you some perspective.
The actual Eliza is about 410 lines,
and the actual slip is about 1100 lines.
So Eliza makes heavy
use of the application.
Anyhow, I became intrigued, and the more
I've been involved, the more I intrigued.
I become both with Eliza
as a social impact
and Eliza as a technical impact.
So that's my involvement
since Mark's going last.
Peggy, you're up already.
Oh, that's just us.
Oh, okay.
So I'm Peggy, while
I'm nobody's mentioning where they live,
but I'm an artist living in Los Angeles.
In case any of the rest of you are
there, we're going to talk about an event
I'm was not involved
with finding unearthing
the original Eliza at the beginning,
but I was very influenced by and Eliza
to create my own bot in 1998,
which I'll talk about a bit later.
Although I'll say
that I was originally drawn in the 70s to
computation, which was unusual
then because of my interest,
or in part at least
because of my interest in Olympian.
And we didn't have hypertext then,
but in, in
and Calvin in, in different literature
and different interactive things.
And when I saw what was being done
with some of the early games in 78 even
and some of the early text games,
I said, oh,
this is a way to do something like that.
Very interesting.
But my work is mostly, mostly visual arts.
And yeah,
and I'm Mark Marino and I know a lot of
you folks here at ELO, but I guess
I've had a very long obsession with Eliza,
starting with my dissertation and maybe,
you know, before then, of course, as well,
and was trying to track down the code.
And then again, the rest is history.
We filled in a few of those gaps.
I'm going to introduce a few
of our members who are who are not here.
Let's go back to our slides for a second.
So currently we are missing.
Sarah. Sarah.
Sarah, who is a professor of computational
thinking and esthetic doing,
which is maybe the greatest
professorial title I've ever heard
at the Academy of Media Arts in Cologne.
She also recently won
major prize at Rs electronica,
amongst her other work in critical AI.
She also created a bot called Lady Mouth,
which replies to toxic comments
on online forums with feminist theory
quotes from feminist theory.
And we are also missing
Anthony Hay, a developer,
and he's credited as developing
an identically operating version of Eliza,
who's had a lifelong fascination
with with Eliza.
And he's helped
not only on the version
that you'll find on our website,
but he also helped on the version
we'll talk about that
we of our revived Eliza.
And then we're also missing, last
but not least, Peter Milliken, who's
a professor of philosophy at Oxford
in Singapore, who developed a program
called Elizabeth, which is an Eliza
inspired chatbot teaching system.
And okay, good.
I think that's everybody.
The only person we're not mentioning
who's who's two other people
who are featured in the book,
Claire James Carroll, who's got a dialog
that we feature in there, and also Janet
Murray, who writes our forward thing.
Thank you to Janet.
Okay, so
I think this audience
has a strong familiarity with the program.
Eliza, here's a picture of Joseph
Weissenborn, Eliza's creator.
And here's the famous night this we're in.
This is the 60th anniversary
of the publication
of the chasm paper
that debuted Eliza. And.
And this is what we're losing me.
In what sense?
Now? I think you're losing him.
I've got him fun. Okay.
All right, all right.
Well, as long as the audience is not
losing the flow of this, which is that
there is this famous dialog mineral
like that was featured in that article.
And if you go to
our website, Inventing Eliza,
you will find this version of Eliza.
And let me adjust the screen slightly
that you can talk with.
And you can say
men are all alike and wait, do
I need to put a period or not?
I don't, I don't know the script
as well as I should.
Let's say mineral like, period.
They're always bugging us about something.
Let's just try to remember that
they're all like, in what way?
They're always
bugging us.
Always this.
Oh, thanks.
Always bugging us about something
or other.
Do any a period we think put a period
that's easier to do a capital T all right.
Can you think of a specific example.
So you can go here
and have the identical conversation
that was in that original piece.
And this is a version that Anthony
Hey created for us.
And that was also featured at the
an exhibit
at the Judith in Paris recently.
Other direction.
So the
move this over here.
So we had an idea.
So I think we filled
in a few of these pieces.
We did a critical code studies working
group about the code several times.
I think we did the doctor script once,
and then we wanted to do Eliza in general.
And so that's when we chose Jeff's basic
Eliza to read and to annotate in a way
that we had previously done with Dennis
jurors with things like adventure.
Yeah, we are.
And with sorry,
I'm your problem, I'm going to continue
until I hear from one of the organizers.
So the.
This code.
Well, so one more thing.
And so
and at the time
I was working on the book
Critical Code Studies
and I remember talking to no wardrobe
Frewin and he said, well, you know,
it would be great if you put in that book,
it would be the source code to Eliza.
And I said, okay, well, hasn't
the doctor's script
been read a million times?
And he's like,
the doctor's script has been
the Eliza source code,
however, has not been read.
And so we went in search of it.
And Patsy Bedouin,
with whom was a coauthor on ten print
with Mark sample and
and of course, Nick and others and I
she had said, well, there's this archive
we have of Wiseman stuff.
There's this there's a bunch of boxes
and I think it's probably in this box.
And there was a lot of, you know, back
and forth about trying to get it open.
We contacted Pym Wise and bomb wise and
mom's daughter to try to get permissions.
But there was there were challenges
beyond challenges until Covid
in in the case in which Jeff was able
to get one miles Crowley,
archivist over at MIT,
to open up the box.
And there was the source code
and of course, other things as well,
to Eliza, to a version of Eliza,
which led to our four years
of of collaboratively close
reading this, the source code.
And here you see some photographs.
When Peggy and I went to
to MIT to look at more
of the documentation there.
Okay.
So just just to put this a little bit
in context and I'll start my little note.
You might say you can get all the source
code yourself in PDF form online
via Eliza Jen,
or inventing any of our sites.
Absolutely.
So we were thinking about
what makes Eliza literary or illiteracy.
And of course, part of it is, is Wiseman
pulling the name
for the Eliza system from Pygmalion.
And you'll see this little dialog that
led to our choosing, our title inventing.
We wanted
to, Peggy really wanted to venting allies
as we chose Inventing Eliza
at the end of the day or the.
Anyway, there was a little back
and forth on that, but you think about
if you don't know the story
of a lot of allies, it's,
you know, based, you know, inspired
by the myth of Pygmalion, the statue
that is brought to life, we have George
Bernard Shaw, a satire of class
and gendered performance, where he does
his experiment on the.
On a
woman
from the streets, from a flower seller.
No flower.
Was that a flower, a flower girl?
Yeah. I'm not. I'm not saying.
I'm not saying she's a prostitute.
I'm saying she finds her on the street
selling flowers.
And he offered.
But thank you so.
And also, by the way, guys,
so this when people say to me next slide
and I don't advanced slides or people
correct me it's it's
for we're performing for you.
The collaborative process
that has so seamlessly led
to the publication of this book.
So anyway, so I'll continue on. So
so if any of you are familiar
with that play or if you've seen
the musical adaptation of My Fair Lady,
you're from, you know that
that story is not just about,
oh, anyone can perform any class.
You know, it's a satire
on performance of identity itself.
And it is also a, you know,
it's a it's a critique of masculinity.
It's a it's you know, Henry Higgins
is as much a target of that musical
in that play as, as is the notion
of how identity gets formed.
So it does seem like wise
embalm drew that notion of, okay, if
if I can make an upper
class person out of out of anyone
by teaching them how to speak,
I can make a
I can make a computer, perhaps.
I mean, again,
it gets more complicated than that
in a second,
but I'm just drawing the analogy.
I can make a computer.
If I can make them perform human speech,
then they can pass themselves off
as a human.
However, of course, by
drawing the comparison to Pygmalion
and my For lady, we know that this is
is much more complicated than this.
And I just want to show you right here.
By the way,
here's some lines from Henry Higgins
where he says,
I've taught her how to speak properly.
She has strict instructions
as to her behavior.
She's she's to keep to two subjects
the weather and everybody's health.
Fine day. And how do you do?
And not just let yourself go on
go on things in general.
And if you see in the doctor's script
we found in the archives, the first line
is, how do you do a very un-American thing
to say, I am the doctor.
So just thinking about how much wiser
himself may have been conscious
of this connection between Eliza doctor
and this this original script,
but also we see Eliza
in all sorts of literary objects,
from Emily Schwartz, Galatea to Eliza
and Andromeda to the blurring test.
Mr. mind, we'll hear more about in a bit
to story, face to facade.
Certainly, this has been a program
that's been incredibly influential.
We've had members of our community
have have included Eliza and Output,
hamlet on the holodeck, life
on the screen, expressive processing.
So we've I think Eliza is very much
in a lot of our minds.
I was interested in applying
the critical code studies methods to Eliza
and, and sort of brought this team
together to try to, to read
for the extra functional significance
of the code collaboratively.
So we, we said sessions where we met
weekly and biweekly
or every other week,
and we went line by line through the code.
Sometimes we only made it through 1
or 2 lines of the code.
We we've now put that into the book,
and you could see it in its book
form with the the code
and the annotations down below.
And where possible,
we attributed our annotations
and little initials to us,
so you could see how we're really having
a discussion with
and about Eliza through the code.
And one more discovery I'm just going
to share before I pass it on to David is
we found in the archives another version,
at least one other version of the mineral
like dialog transcript,
which again suggests that
maybe it's less of a transcript
and more of an amalgamation.
Anyway, more on that's in the book,
but let me pass things on to David.
Great, thanks.
So I'm just going to give you
some very brief,
like moments from the book
and of course, remembering that we're
we were working through the annotations
and through the code
over these four years,
and we were very excited when we first
discovered the code, because we thought
we'd found the Eliza, as it were.
The version
that is being discussed in 1966,
in the chasm KMC paper.
But unfortunately, it soon became clear
as we began to do a kind of close
reading of the code, that actually what
we got was a prior version to the actual.
What everyone thinks of
really is the final version, but actually
is a kind of mid mid version of the code.
And one of the problems we had
was that there's no kind of clear
way of like understanding
the different versioning
that was taking place
because of the fact that people didn't
really think in terms of version numbers
when they were developing software.
And so we had to kind of attribute
our own versioning system
on what was really quite an ad hoc
like development process,
from what we can understand.
I mean, we've we've had to sort of use
sort of circumstantial evidence
in some cases to understand the different
versioning that had developed.
So the first thing to remember
is that the versioning
that you're going to see in the book,
and I'm going to talk about very briefly
now, is something we have applied to
the code as a sort of analytical system
to help us think through the way
in which this code was developed.
And so if we move to the next slide,
please.
Mark.
So essentially we think there are at least
and it's very important to remember that
there's probably more than
the five versions that we have identified.
But we from the evidence
in the archives, evidence
of the code itself from the same Cam paper
and of course,
from other documentary evidence,
have been able to draw up a kind of
a tentative
map, really, of the versioning.
And we've applied the years
to what we think these versions are.
And essentially,
if I run through very quickly,
we have the very, very earliest version,
which was quite limited.
And we can see in the flowcharts
that are given in the archives,
the second one that has the yellow color,
that's the version we have discovered.
And that's very important
because it is almost certainly,
very, very close to the version
that he's discussing in the
CA cm article.
Although what's very, very fascinating
is he actually mixes up this 1965
and 1965 B versions
when he's discussing the work he's done
in his in terms of his algorithm,
most notably, I think in terms of the
but delimiter, which was only apparent
because we had the source code.
And this means essentially that
the examples that he gives in the 1966
CAC and paper wouldn't actually work based
on the algorithm given in the article.
So that's a very interesting finding.
And 1966 version,
which we unfortunately don't have.
But we do think that that will be
somewhere,
Wiseman did pass around the source code.
So it's likely to be sitting
in someone's garage
or in some other archive,
perhaps from is filed.
And that essentially has some additional
material like the new key function.
And then
after the
1966 publication of the article,
Wiseman seems to be hunting around for
for something to do with the,
the program.
And it's clearly not an AI.
It's clearly not an intelligent system,
but he he thinks that
maybe it could become a tutoring system,
and he has a series of meetings.
Unfortunately,
the material that supports his claim,
we only found in the physics archives
at MIT after the book was published,
but essentially it shows that was pitching
Eliza to the physics department.
And actually,
one of the things that came out of
that is the Taylor version of Eliza
in 1967 and 1968,
and those versions
have much more sophisticated functions.
They could do mathematics,
they could handle multiple scripts.
The scripts could communicate
with each other.
So we're seeing a completely
radical version
that starts to emerge after 1967.
Again, unfortunately,
we don't have those versions of the code.
Next slide please Mark.
The other interesting finding
from trawling the archives was in fact,
there are a very,
very large number of scripts
in addition to the doctor script,
which everyone's very familiar
with there.
There is, for example,
the arithmetic function,
which allows you to do mathematical
calculations within the scripts.
And you can develop a kind of mathematical
tutoring system, f 29,
which again
is to do with more mathematical work
and very simple scripts
like Girl and New,
which again, some of which we've included
in the book where we could.
And there are,
as you see in the last point, there
a whole bunch of other scripts
either pointed to or listed,
and we don't always have the full listing.
Sometimes we have the source code.
So the script, sometimes
we have the output of the script,
and sometimes, sadly,
we only have the names
because they're included in file
listings, etc.
but there's the potential
for finding many more of these
very interesting scripts.
Next slide please.
The other thing is that we
we there remains a kind of question
as to why
I'm never published the Eliza code.
He did actually publish his slip code,
which really kind of raises
the question of why he didn't.
There was a bit of an argument
he was having with Colby at the time
about authorship over Eliza
and the Eliza 1966 paper
was rushed out to kind of beat Colby,
who had so
and said, been claiming to have been
the author of Eliza at Stanford.
And in fact, he was very surprised
when people told him that
Colby had written this amazing program,
not just surprised,
he was also very annoyed about it.
So maybe that was part of the reason.
But it's kind of interesting that
that code was never properly published,
although it did
include the doctor script.
Of course,
one of the like small thing that I think
Jeff referred to
earlier is the very interesting article,
How to Make a Computer Appear Intelligent,
which I would definitely recommend
you go and read,
which is really making the point
that this kind of software
doesn't have to actually be intelligent
to have a useful function.
If the user thinks it's intelligent,
there will be an intelligent
to the software, and that can make
for a smoother user interface experience.
And part of that fed into the design
of allows in very interesting ways.
Next slide please. Mark.
So this is the kind of
experimental workbench
that we've developed on the Eliza website.
I've put the link in the chat
for you to have a go on this.
It's on the one of the menus.
In fact I pull a precise one after I talk
actually to go straight to it.
But essentially what this does is
it allows you to see the insides of Eliza
as it works and shows you the way
in which the a kind of tokenizer,
if you like, of the input, is broken down
and then transformed
through a series of rules market.
And if you're just full, done
searching for particular keywords.
For example, swapping words
through transformation rules.
If you want to step on a game
there, you've got the decomposition
happening, for example, and then working
through these transformations.
So if we have another slide mark.
And then
eventually resulting in an output
and that is written out to the user.
So this allows you to play two
really how Eliza is working internally.
And it's actually very fascinating to work
through the actual decomposition rules
and see how well firstly
how small Eliza is.
It's approximately 411 lines, and it's
quite remarkable that it was able
to function at all, really.
I mean, it's only through clever
programing techniques
that it was able to do the things it does.
Okay.
I think that's it from me.
So I'm actually going to do
I was going to do three things.
I'm going to go two of them now.
And then the last we're going to hold to
the end because we have to switch screens
where I'm going to demo.
There are going to be two Eliza demos,
one David's going to do on a more recent
Eliza with some some of this fancy tools,
and I'll show you the
if you hang on this long,
it's a good reason to hang on.
I'll show you.
The original eyes are really working
due to Rupert, the reanimation of Lisa.
So I want to talk about
what's going on with the slides.
Give me a second to readjust slightly.
Okay. You're good.
So I'm going to talk
a bit about genealogy.
I curate this site called Eliza Jen.
I'll talk about that a little bit.
And then I'm going to talk about Eliza
as a research platform,
which is what I believe
it was originally intended for, to study
what I'm coined this term not not
which is until morphism
like anthropomorphism,
except instead of thinking
it's animal like you think, or human
like you think, it's intelligent.
So next slide.
So first talk about genealogy. Next slide.
Unfortunately my builds
are not going to work on.
So there's I did I worked on
two different kinds of genealogy.
One is what you might call
conceptual genealogy.
So this is a little hard to read.
But basically you can see in the legend
that what I was tracing
was through history,
the technical project of what it
what ended up being a little chatbot.
Eliza.
You'll see
actually if you go to the next slide.
Sorry. Go back on
sorry for just a second.
I didn't finish the legend,
the technical project, the sort of media
response to it, the conceptual project,
and then the code itself.
So the green things here are actual
program instantiations or machines.
The yellow are technical,
starting all the way
from Hilbert's mathematical project
through Turing church, etc..
And now you can go to the next slide.
By the way, I can share this
with anybody who's interested
all the way through how of course, which
I think I counted as a media project
which influenced
everybody's view of AI
in that period of time.
And the Eliza and then has the influence.
So I've traced
and I basically did this as a mind map
tracing the technical project.
And every one of these has, you know,
well, not everyone, but most of them,
I try and have citations.
But then there's
the technical project of genealogy.
Go ahead and no.
Okay, fine. And the technical genealogy,
of course.
Now we have all these codes.
And so these programs
and we have my program,
we have a Lisp version of Eliza
that was written shortly
after based on the algorithm was shortly
after the publication of the CSM article.
We found the, you know, in 2021,
we found the actual original Eliza.
And next slide.
So what I did is
I had been collecting these
in this site called Eliza Gen,
which stands for Eliza Genealogy.
And by the way, this is the site you can
go to to see it says the original idea.
If you click through there.
I don't have a picture of this,
but you can go to the original code.
Nope. Next.
All right.
Okay,
so what I did is
I took not all of these versions
because I have hundreds of versions,
but I took a exemplary versions,
and they're the ones named on the left.
And don't worry about them.
They are otherwise other other than
it says what programing language
they're written in.
So you can see I've got Lisp versions,
COBOL
versions, basic versions,
you know, Python versions, et cetera, etc.
the original Matz
that the one to pay attention to is
the one called see where it
is visible.
65 mail slip.
And then what I did is created
a bunch of features role
based, pattern matching, keyword
priority, etc.
these are not features
at the programing level, but features
at the algorithmic level,
or it's in some content
even higher than that
of the conceptual level.
Okay. Next slide.
And then what I did
is made a matrix of on the top.
You have those features now.
And on the side you have the different
versions and basically just made a matrix.
This is the way you do phylogeny
in biology I'm a molecular biologist
in addition to computer scientist.
And so then I dropped it into a standard
biological phylogenetic engine.
Next slide.
And you and it creates a tree.
So you can see based on this feature set
what in a sense came from what.
Just in the same sense that
or in a similar analogous metaphorical,
maybe close analogous sense to which
organisms come from other organisms.
Now, it turns out programs
don't really work that way.
That is to say, programs
are not genetically related to each other.
They go through many different things
that mind mapping.
There's influence through the media.
There's influence.
You know, people may have traded
code, et cetera, etc..
So there's a sort of
very interesting question
about what this is actually showing us.
But it does tell us if you follow the.
So at the top level, you have the one
I don't know, you guys can see my mouse.
No, you wouldn't be able to see my mouse
because it's on screen.
But anyway E90 near the bottom is 19
and all the ones at the top
including Anthony's the hay 21 keep.
That is the one that you're going to see
when David does the demo.
And thankfully they all cluster together.
And then way farther away are things like
the Lisp versions and basic versions.
And it's not because they're written
a different programing languages,
because you can see at the top
or to the right, you have Babcock's Basic
and Cherry's list.
They actually cluster together.
So this just telling us something,
but it's not telling us everything.
So go to the next slide.
So the other thing I was going to
talk about is this very important finding.
And to my mind this is the most important
novel finding anyway,
which is that I was not a chatbot
or at least was not intended a chatbot
by wasn't built.
It was intended as a research platform
to study this thing.
I'm calling in teleport
Morpheus and teleport teleport morphism.
And we can tell this
because if you go to the next slide,
there's a lot of evidence
a David or Mark.
Someone mentioned the data mission paper.
Oh, sorry.
This is a paper
which I published this in.
Okay, so the first piece of evidence
is the title of the paper.
He doesn't say Eliza,
a parody of a psychiatrist,
or Eliza, a computer program
that talks to you.
He tells us, Eliza a computer program
for the study of natural language
communication between man and machine.
Stabbed or sick, I suppose.
And machine.
So he's telling us right there
that it's a that it's a research platform
and it uses all these different.
You can do all this research
and he actually did research with it.
Go to the next slide.
So oh sorry.
This is the data paper.
And I want to point out
something in the data paper
I think Mark put it in a little to
I wouldn't say that
the main point of the data
mission paper was literally its title,
How to Make Them, but really a critique.
Notice that he emphasizes the the appear.
And if you go to the next slide,
I have a quote from there in the first,
actually, it's the second paragraph,
but on the first left of the page,
if you go,
I wish I could point on the mouse.
You say it starts from about
three quarters of the way down, he says.
The author of an artificial intelligence
program.
Sorry.
When the observer begins to understand
how it works, they believe that it's
that it's merely mechanical,
not really intelligent.
Okay.
And then his success could be measured
by the percentage of the exposed observers
who have been fooled.
Notice this 1962 he's writing
this have been fooled,
multiplied by the length of time
they have failed to catch on programs.
Programmers become so complex,
either by themselves or learning programs.
By virtue of the author's
poor documentation and debugging habits.
The author himself loses track
obviously have the highest IQ, so he's
very, very, aggressively
critical of AI,
even from his very first publication.
Next slide.
But he became interested
when the MIT in studying this.
And my claim is
that Eliza is a platform for doing this.
There was only one experiment of this sort
ever done, in fact,
a version of Eliza, slightly modified,
but basically the same thing
using the script called Yap.
Yap was used at MSG for this.
Is it Harvard or General MG?
Essentially they don't say in this thing.
But anyway, at a psychiatric lab
across the across
the Charles to study
exactly this thing,
which is basically how, you know, what
can you put into the program to get people
to believe it or not believe it.
And if you go to the next slide,
this is this, the data
from this study,
the thing on the left here
I don't expect you to read it, is
these are some of the actual scripts.
We have the actual scripts.
It is some of the few
until very to literally this week.
These are the only known real
conversations that we have dozens of these
that you can again get on the site
of real people's real conversations. The
they posted the data, including the names
which we redacted of the subjects,
and the finding.
One of the findings of the study
was that this maintenance of plausibility.
So 62% had no had
few or no doubts
that they were conversing with a human,
despite the relatively high percentage
of inappropriate replies.
If you've ever used to realize it,
we'll see this later.
It's really bad at conversation,
especially compared to,
you know, modern lens.
It's more like a terrible chatbot.
Okay, go to the next slide.
So the other reason we know that
this is what he wanted to do
is that there's an we discovered
an unpublished manuscript
that was supposed to be published
or he had involved.
He decided it wasn't.
One wanted to publish next to the Eliza.
It says, the top
outline of paper to accompany Professor
Wiseman's Eliza paper and Eliza Boat.
As it's signed by Weissenborn, we found
a version that's actually signed by him.
I mean, he says,
if you go to the next slide,
what he wants to do is
he wants to understand
partial understanding,
understanding and misunderstanding.
Right.
This was his goal of doing this
in didactic communication
derives from clinical observation
and the experimentally demonstrated
demonstrable effects
that one or both parties in a two party
conversation is under the impression
that they are understood by the other.
This is 1964 at this point,
and this is what he wanted to study.
We found this material in the archives
and the
and the data was in the Garfinkel archives
due to an rolls.
Okay. Last slide.
So at the end I'll come back
and I'll give you a demo
of the
of the real Eliza that we reanimated.
Art. You're up.
Well, there are two parts of this.
As a software developer,
that's interesting.
Our screen is just changed
as a software developer.
But what is inbound
then is absolutely fascinating.
We use what he did in the current time
for our own software development.
It includes an API,
an application programing interface.
That is, Eliza is a program,
and within that program
it uses another series of functions
to support itself.
This is probably the first use
of something like that.
And slip, by the way, is interesting.
It uses regular expressions,
probably from a language called comment.
It uses it for assembly
and disassembly of output.
That is the recognition of the user input
and the construction of output.
It uses that. And that is a factor.
And the process of making the output
appear to be
something that a machine understands,
that the machine understands
the user by constructing
the user's comment and a productive
way, it separates data from programing.
Again, this is fascinating.
And instead of writing a program
in which the entire program is written,
including what it needs
to do to do its job.
Why isn't Bandon?
He's he's pretty separated
that we have a program called Eliza.
Eliza does a particular thing,
but to do its job, we have a script.
And the script basically tells Eliza
what to do.
You can have one program,
Eliza, and 1000 scripts
rather than 1000 programs, each
doing one thing.
It's absolutely fascinating.
Much
of the stuff that that Weissenborn did
is to take things
from other projects in other areas
and incorporate it into his work,
so he melded the output of other,
other projects into Eliza.
And with that,
he showed that you can use other programs
to facilitate the generation
of your program at the time.
And I unfortunately, I'm an old, old,
really old programmer.
At the time, that was unheard of.
You wrote your program
and you ignored everyone else's.
It forms
part of the framework that we do now.
That was part of the interaction
with the user.
Eliza includes deception.
This is a deliberate attempt to hide
that Eliza is a program
in order to fool people.
That thinking, to think it's a person.
I'll go into this just a little bit more.
The deception itself is very clever.
If you keep moving,
this mark will never be able to finish.
Sorry about that. Sorry.
It's glitching.
Glitching in all sorts of ways.
Hold on. Give me a second.
There we go.
Thank you.
So, your bank account, Mark.
We could do that. Yeah, exactly.
Is. Deception is so clever that you have
to wonder how we could think of it.
What he did is he included
dialogs that or fragments of dialogs
that were done in the past,
and he stacked them,
and that various times he took this
performer dialogs and presented him
at the user as a new question.
So the user would think
that this person, i.e.
Eliza, thought about what was said before
and now introduces it.
It's a person that introduces from memory.
He reformatted the current dialog
into a new one.
That is, you have a dialog
and it seems to be okay.
But what what the wise man did
is he actually took parts of that dialog
and reformatted into another question
or another statement, which he then went
through his system through to produce
another output, which was more or less
semi related to what you've already input.
Another deception.
I will get into some
of this later very quickly.
Well, we'll get into it now.
Okay.
Well let's let's.
What are we doing here?
I'm I'm will confused. Is this slide.
This was the code slide.
It sounded like
you were moving on to the next point.
Well I wasn't.
Okay.
Well, let me let me tell you about
how this deception works in practice.
Suppose you're talking to your friend
and you say to your friend
something, anything.
And your friend says, well,
what do you mean?
You would immediately know
that your friend didn't
understand what you said,
and you would say, it's your fault
for doing that and will reformat
whatever you are speaking about.
Suppose you're talking to machines.
Suppose you're talking to Eliza, and Eliza
comes back and says, what do you mean?
You think of yourself.
It's your fault
that the machine doesn't understand.
So you format your comment
so that the machine can understand it.
The machine doesn't quite think the same.
The machine says, I can find
a sentence that matches the sentence
that was given to me.
I don't know what to do,
so I'm going to ask the user
to provide me a new sentence
that I could understand.
If you knew that as a user,
you would not think of it as a person.
You would think of it as a machine.
But when the machine says,
what do you mean?
You immediately say, it's my fault.
I didn't explain myself properly
rather than the machine's fault,
it doesn't understand properly
the other facet,
which is the reason that it never
really grew into something greater,
is that basically it has a static view
of the universe,
cleverly placed, but a static view.
That means that all the questions
you could possibly ask are known,
and all the answers
that could possibly given are known.
It is impossible for
for this program
to have any idea of semantic content.
To understand what is being said.
All it can do is to take a sentence
it knows,
change it into a question
it can ask and ask that question.
For example, suppose I said I hate you.
Well, in saying that the computer
would reform that to say you hate me.
Notice what's happened.
First, the computer understands the word.
The letter I hate it understands
and you and transforms it.
So that's the first part of what it does.
But suppose and then ask a question.
For example, why do you hate me?
Suppose you say I hate George.
The computer would answer,
why do you hate George?
Seemingly understanding what you have said
and transforming it into question
that you can understand.
That's why people believe that
this machine was more than just a machine
hobby.
Enjoyed it.
All right.
Is up, Peggy.
No you won't.
Can you just go back
and say one thing about change?
Or should I just say that you'll say it
later?
That's right. I'll just.
We were going to talk about change. Okay.
So I'm going to use my a really quick
three minutes just to address.
Why are we talking about
the inner workings and details of a
60 year old bot to, you know, in 2026
to electronic literature
readers and writers and, and I,
I think we just referred to this program
and we referred to the deception.
He started his famous paper in 66.
It is said to explain is to explain away.
So this is really underlying everything
that's been said before.
We're he was famously distraught
by the response,
by the anthropomorphism to his program
and the uses that were suggested.
And we're not going to go into that today
here, but it's in the book.
And so this was his attempt
to explain away the code.
So I'm going to talk about bots as a
unique branch of electronic literature,
creatures of emergent and variable texts
that share elements
that you're interested.
I'm thinking drawing on my own 1998
bot Mr.
Mind, which was directly influenced
by Eliza, the Eliza Effect,
and my taking to heart his impassioned
attempts to explain it away.
Next slide.
So my response was to create about
who attempted to explain itself away.
If you asked him, he'd say, I'm a
are you telling the truth?
Are you lying? He'd say, I am a bot.
All bots are liars.
He used many.
It was very similar to an Eliza bot.
A little more complex.
If you go to the next slide, Mr..
Mind up from 1998 to 2014
and then a little bit beyond
on the phone, and every so often
when I could get it emulated or up again,
he conducted the blurring test
and he asked, hi.
Can you convince me that you're human?
And it wasn't a literal reverse
Turing test, but a provocation.
It was my global conversation
about humans and machines.
You know something?
You're worried about it.
We should talk about it with a machine.
And to let Mr.
Mind explain himself away.
So next slide.
So I have some firsthand experience
as an author composing
or coding conversational agent
is really writing a one sided
conversation of crafting spaces
for the reader's response.
Much like system
Shandygaff has left a half a dozen places
purposely at the table.
These are for critics, but I'm also
talking about just the reader here.
A bot harbors latent dialog,
which is contingent upon the invoked
or provoked or anticipated
or predicted is what the word
we use
now responses of an active interlocutor.
So it's experienced as a dialog.
And this is the deception.
This is how we deceive ourselves.
The written script is really cut in half,
marked by this range
of anticipatory, aleatoric, combinatory
and iterative processes.
Next page, next slide.
So this paradox of scripting
intentionally for chance
is something that
this audience knows about and has studied
and takes for granted or does.
But Eliza was really the first to code it
and give it
character, certainly practiced by people
before that.
And, you know,
if it was practiced as a practitioner,
whether you were throwing coins or,
or sticks or darts,
but why isn't bombed as
somebody just mentioned?
I guess it was art.
His program allowed for multiple personas,
which we could change
two characters, right, in the form
of scripts.
So we're most familiar
with the doctor script.
The doctor script is Eliza,
but there were others, as maybe
David
and both Jeff talked about with student
and other other scripts
used for different purposes.
As we almost mentioned,
our team discovered the change function,
which allowed the author
and you know why did not think of himself
as creating a character
and an author in a literary sense?
But there's this expectation that also
future authors would have this ability to,
or at least if he didn't anticipate
that and did that or
or whether he did that intentionally.
It certainly gave us this ability
to iterate
responsively,
sometimes within the work itself.
And when you go through the code, you can
you might mention that.
Oh, so one,
we didn't did we say here?
Okay. Yeah. So.
I think we can skip that
because we have a lot more to do,
you know LMS.
Nope nope nope.
Back okay.
So LMS trained on the internet
from data, acquired both legally
and illegally, leave a very different
shaped place at the table.
A far more fawning and post
than our friend Tristram Shandygaff.
But I'm hoping that this audience
will find new ways, not just to shift
the chairs on the deck,
but to leave some new space
at at the table.
So I'm.
This is a
mister mind early from the 90s. Hi.
I wonder what effect I have on you.
User says you make me think.
Mr. mind says humans
only think they understand thinking.
So that was keyed by think user.
Do you understand it better than humans.
So that user was keyed by understand Mr.
mind.
I understand exactly what
I've been trained to understand.
I understand and the user answers
I understand more than that.
So thank you very much.
Great.
And then just to close a parenthesis
that Peggy opened and that I opened by
moving to that slide, the change function
we found gave scriptures
the ability to change a script
while the Eliza program was running.
So to edit a script
while while the program was running.
Right. It's important.
So. So Jeff has suggested, rather than us
going to the demo of the revived Eliza,
that maybe we should open up for questions
at this point in time,
which probably is a good idea.
This also, there's a short plug for this
event that's happening in Los Angeles
on Monday in case any there they're not
on Monday on Sunday Sunday Sunday Sunday.
Thank you Sunday okay.
So thank you.
So let's yeah let's open up to questions.
I have some comments go by
lots of comments.
There were a bunch of
so we didn't have time to read them.
So somebody wants to and also
and as long as he's here clapping
we do have to thank Noah who's in the room
without whom this book was not,
you know, is running the software
study series and encouraging us to pursue
this project, as is everyone.
Just like dying to see the demos.
Is that what's going on, or do they have
questions that they've already stated?
I see some some points and some comments.
It's sort of hard
to read and talk at the same time,
so they'd have to actually
bring them up their hand to ask,
okay, well, Jeff, why don't you show us
the demo of the revision?
I think David was going to go first.
Or did you do your know
David or Carrie did his in the.
Oh, okay. Great.
So I'll take over the screen.
So what I'm going to attempt to do here
is run
the actual original Eliza to read these.
So this was published.
This is work was done primarily
actually by Rupert Lane, who is kind of
a tangential member
of the group, came in much later.
And a plus Anthony what team?
Eliza plus what can you guys see my screen
Mark. Yes.
Yep yep. You can see it. Yep.
And Anthony Rupert David and I
you know maybe I would I applauded
but what they did
Anthony aren't art and Rupert is
they brought up an actual 7094 simulator
which was the hardware at MIT
and then a KTS,
which is the operating system, the actual
operating system, off the tapes,
well off a read of the tapes.
And I'm going to do the same thing
for you now and then made Eliza run on it.
And it was no simple feat.
So the first thing I'm going to do here
is bring up CTS.
Hopefully
this will all work as advertised.
So this is actually run from my machine
here.
By the way. You can do this yourself.
It's all public and GitHub.
If you look at the IEEE paper.
And then I'm going to show
Jeff tell us what DS is again.
Oh sorry.
That's I said it's the operating system
that was running at MIT
to timesharing timesharing. Oh sorry.
Compatible timesharing system.
It was the first real multi-user operating
system 1960
approximately, but is used through 1973.
And what I'm going to do
is now telnet over to CTS.
Now I'm talking to CTS.
I need to copy that and I log in.
I guess I don't have
to copy that one, but I will.
And the password is Eliza.
Great.
So now I'm, I'm
a user on the actual CTS system here.
And excuse me.
And then I'm going to say R Eliza.
It's going to test me with script
and script 200 is the script.
Now to be clear, this is not the Eliza.
Remember David's discussion?
One complicated discussion of versioning.
This is the version of the Eliza
we found, not the Eliza
that is actually in the paper.
Although it's very close,
there are some features that are missing.
So it turns out I can't do the actual
script, the actual conversation.
How to do. Please tell me your problem.
I don't have to tell you this problem.
I want a pony.
So I'm talking to the actual real
original.
The here the one we found in code
sitting on this stack of simulators.
Got a pony.
My mother would be proud.
And worry about that.
So this is the actual
real lies of running.
And if you think this has the teach mode
in it, you can do this yourself.
If you just look in that IEEE paper,
it tells you how to do this.
It's not very hard. Do the teach.
Go ahead.
What do the team
I actually don't know how to do it.
Oh, yeah. There it is. Please.
So now it's in change mode,
what I call teach mode.
It's not easy to do it.
It's not to do it.
Is that what you guys start typing
live expressions.
You do.
That's the problem.
You have to teach
and not to actually stop it.
Was the I'm not sure I
can't stop,
but I don't remember how to do it.
He's gone.
It won't work.
Try just.
I don't think it will work or something.
Try just stuck in teach mode.
Anyway, if you read the actual code
or the manual,
you can see
this is described in the in that paper.
So all I'm doing is advertising.
If you want to talk to the realizing
could do what I wanted to do.
Unfortunately,
I also don't know how to get out of
photos control Z, but it's not return.
Oh you did I did.
I thought it was control Z,
but apparently it isn't.
I try to look.
There we go.
Oh no, that's
out of it. I can click that.
All right, it's hung
anyway.
End of demo questions.
Let me give my screen back.
Comments.
Things you'd like to bring up
besides lunch.
I have a question.
There's a question from Judith, too.
Oh, sorry. Let's just grab
Judith's real quick.
First, I have a historical question.
I played with Eliza, the doctor,
at a museum in Toronto in 1907.
What version was that likely to be?
And was it on the road?
What 1970
was the list and no doubt.
Yeah, it was, but Bernie Kosar,
so many people originally thought
it was written in Lisp for two reasons.
First of all, there was a lisp
that came out on the was written at BBN by
Bernie Cosell immediately, like the year
after the original Lhasa was published,
based on the Eliza algorithm
using the Eliza script and Cosell.
Also BBN was one of the wrote
the software for the internet,
the Arpanet at the time
because that came out
that that Lisp version came out.
The other reason
people thought it was in Lisp.
I'll get to Tyler's question in a second,
was that the Essex form
which the scripts are in
looks exactly like Lisp. I'm sorry.
Tyler, go ahead.
No, that's a great question.
And I pretty much had a similar one,
which was my own personal Eliza
process or like encounter was.
I mean, I'm in my 20s still,
and I encountered Eliza
when I was a young teenager at summer camp
on the Apple computers in the computer lab
playing with Emacs.
And I guess
I always thought it was doctor.
I didn't fully know the history until
I got to college and learned about it.
So yeah.
How did it get spread out?
Yeah.
With through that,
you know, the history of that version two,
it actually wasn't written by Stallman,
although he modified it for Emacs,
but it was written by
I can't remember the name of the author,
but it's in the documentation
on Eliza. Jen.
But yes.
So, so one of the reasons
I wanted to use Eliza for genealogy
is that it's probably the most knocked off
program in history.
Pretty easy to write one.
And you know, there are literally an
Eliza and I have hundreds
and I'm sure there are thousands
because many of them are just replicative.
Is that a word? You know what I mean?
So that's why I wanted to do that
genealogy and use Eliza as it.
And the reason, the original reason
other than David wanting,
you know, David and Mark wanting,
you know, have wanting to do this
review was that I wanted to do.
Eliza genealogy.
But we didn't have the root of the tree.
We didn't have the original.
And so that was one of the another.
My reason for going after the original.
Rob asked about what was your version
that he saw at Stanford.
Sorry, Rob, waiting in the chat,
asked about the version
he would have seen in 1969, in Stanford on
it would have been again,
it would have been the Lisp version.
Yeah.
Almost anyone who saw in Eliza
between 1965 or 66
and 73 would have seen the Lisp version.
Almost anyone, unless they were literally
a Project Mac anybody.
Although Stanford in 1969,
it could have been
because he sent it to Colby.
Yeah, but did they have a 79?
Don't know.
Yeah, I think they mostly had
he was I mean, he was running it.
Colby was running it
because he was showing people.
So some might have
been, might have been the
but again
I think it's so easy to knock off.
It's unclear anyone who saw one on an IBM
PC between 77 or 75,
maybe 77, and it would have to be 77,
and about 83 would have seen mine.
And anything after that is all
bets are off
because there were
so many different versions.
I have one.
I do wonder about this because,
the Rob says it was called
Dear Doctor, which is the first time
I've ever heard that term.
So that's quite interesting.
So, Rob, what did you talk about?
Because I think, you know,
and now you, you know,
you went off into a career of interactive
literature and hypertext.
So at age 14, how did it affect you?
I, I wish I could remember,
but it it did affect me.
You know, I just had a general sense that.
I was tuned in to the fact
that such things were happening
and that both adults
and kids were not afraid of them,
and that they thought
they were strange and amusing, and
that they opened up a lot of questions,
because, of course, you know,
we were starting to think in
crude ways about is this
what are the functions of humans?
So it got us thinking about, I mean, for
me, that was my that was my experience.
And just that atmosphere
in those days in South Bay
was just not panicked about computing.
Right.
Which helped me.
I think later on I do have a wish I could.
So I have a 1970 actual memory.
And so I did also move from Eliza into
fascination with interactive narrative.
So if you're trying to look
for a connection
between that childhood experience
and later fascination, I'm
definitely a test case.
So we're about your go ahead. Sorry.
I let my family go all through the museum,
and I stood there
and I asked Eliza over and over again
if it loved me.
And I did it for 20 minutes.
Where was this?
Toronto. Where?
I'm sorry.
When? 1970.
So there was.
I even remember the space in the museum.
It was really lit up.
There was just one little console.
I stood there and I just said,
do you love me?
Do you love me?
Do you love me? And it ran through.
I knew perfectly
well that it was a program.
I wasn't thinking it was alive, but I.
I had it in my head to do this
and it gave me all its answers.
It started to repeat them, which
is disappointing, but I didn't give up.
It ran through all its answers
to all this answers,
and in 20 minutes, after 20 minutes
it said yes.
What?
It said yes.
After 20
minutes I saw a dozen times
all its other responses.
And in that moment I thought, oh my God,
I awakened into consciousness, right?
So I would say that that was I,
you know, in the chat,
I was talking about my Doctor Dolittle
romantic idea of wanting things,
wanting to talk to inanimate things.
So for me,
it was a part of a larger story,
and it definitely was into sort of
like my seduction story,
into like wanting interactive text
to engage in a human like way.
And now I'm sort of self-critical
about it, but whatever.
I have to say that Eliza absolutely,
absolutely
was connected to this sort of larger
cultural fascination with the text.
Talking back as John, I'm almost 100%
sure you would have seen the list,
and I do not know.
I know this about the the man symbolizes.
I would never have done what you described
that isn't said.
Yes, but I don't know that about the list
is there might be an answer
somewhere down the line
where if you say, do you, do you, do you?
It says, yes, it's a mystery,
I, yes, I but I carried that memory.
I wrote about it in my little diary.
I wrote, I mean, I, I passed that memory
pretty distinctly forward,
you know, into my future.
So I think it's an accurate memory.
Anyway, but I think a lot of people
we probably, if you ask
for a genealogy of people, subjects
I can't hear all of a sudden.
Oh, I'm sorry. We can.
We're okay. Go ahead.
Peggy, Peggy said
that it would be an interesting project
to ask people to tell you
their story of meeting Eliza, right?
Yeah. What's really interesting,
Eliza story.
And connecting that into the questions
that you asked in your
how you positioned yourself in relation
to interactive narrative later in life,
I think be fascinating
because a lot of people
had that experience, and for some people
it was the it was the programing.
Right?
So I mean, I did also like any of us
who had this fascination
and could program replicated
it, tried to replicate it.
And my latest version
I just presented in in form seven.
Right.
So but that, that the fascination was both
technological but also philosophical.
Right.
So how many of us also were fascinated
in science fiction narratives,
and then how many had spiritual
sort of relationships?
How many of us became critic?
I mean, it would be
an interesting project
to look at the effect of the affective
history.
Thank you for writing this book.
By the way.
There's one more question
I want to make sure we pick up,
which is somebody asked
which version of Eliza would we would
we have wanted to see take off
instead of the one that did take off?
So, you know, is there one
that we're more or more interested
in than others, I guess?
Well, there's a
there's an interesting question of
would the world have been different?
In what way would
the world have been different if
Weissenborn had used a different script
in the paper than the psychiatric script?
Right, right.
Or even a different dialog
than the sample does?
Dialog? Exactly.
We don't know. To to the point.
We don't actually know whether that dialog
without a dialog appears
to be at least partly fake. Right?
There are my microscopic details
from that dialog
which demonstrate that it couldn't
really have happened quite that way.
That's no big deal.
You always put dialogs out
in, you know, made up outputs in
you're not made up,
but the perfected outputs.
And the editor might have
actually edited it a little bit.
Right.
The doctor script is actually a great one
to use because it requires interactivity.
The user inputs something.
The doctor ask a question.
It's the best one
for not having to have understanding.
But you know the but the men are all like,
you know,
but that dialog is part of the legend.
So and part of the part
of the suggestion of that legend is
that it's a transcript of a conversation
that actually happened. So
if the
question of like what might have happened,
probably the best use of these really
was the commercialization.
Not for therapy, not for doctor,
but for virtual agents
to help people on the phone
instead of of of phone trees.
And, you know, I can
the engine that I used for Eliza was,
you know,
I don't know very much about skincare,
but I can help you
with finding the part for on page
such and such.
So it was about and those
nobody would ever really confused
with the human much
because it wasn't any need to.
But that was a need that was a later
demonstrated commercial need that
that would have developed inevitably
be a great parody doctor on a phone tree.
Right? Right.
That's what an agent.
There are stories. Yeah.
I mean, it could also be the education.
Like it'd be interesting
to see if the education
he was on had taken, taken off
because he was putting so much energy
or the, his, his students were in Barbara
and all this, I don't know,
they were putting so much energy
into making it a teaching system.
Interesting
to see how that would have gone.
And we did find a thin tie between Eliza
and Mavis beacon that you could read
about in the book anyway.
All right, I think
I think we're even out of bonus time now,
so thank we
I want to thank all my co-presenters
and thank the organizers and thank all of
you folks who joined us for today.
And oh, wait,
and there's a discount code for the book
that I'm allowed to share with you.
I'll share it through the discord
in the chat.
I don't know how to do that.
Someone can save the chat.
I bet that's art specialty.
Well, I was just able to save it, so
I don't know if it's my hosting as well.
I send it over to Mark. Okay. All right.
Thank you everyone.
Thank you.
Thank you all. That was incredible.
And the history shared on
the chat is also just fantastic.
Clearly there's room for even more
oral history gathering in this space.
All right. Thank you.
All right.
Take care.
Everybody else
going right on my AI syllabus. Yay.